## Caio Moreno de Souza, MSc, MBA

University Professor, Data Scientist and Consultant

caiomsouza@gmail.com

## Summary

Father of two girls, entrepreneur, data scientist, consultant, instructor, blogger, Pentaho DW/BI and Big Data Specialist. Fluent in English, Spanish and Portuguese. Learning IT and FR.

- Working with Pentaho technologies since 2006 (Tested the 1.2 version and implemented a real project in a real client in production using 1.6 GA);
- Specialist in Business Intelligence and Big Data Projects using Pentaho BI Suite and other Open Source Technologies;
- Open Data Volunteer;
- International experience.
- Sales experience.
- Project management experience.
- Product development experience.

Specialties: Open Source Technologies, Business Intelligence, Machine Learning, Artificial Intelligence, Data Warehouse, Data Marts, Pentaho BI Suite, Mondrian, Java, PostgreSQL, Linux, Big Data, Hadoop, Spark, Pig, Hive, R, SAS, Python and Open Data.

Certified Specialist - Pentaho Business Analytics Certified Specialist - Pentaho Data Integration

Nationality: Brazilian and Spanish.

## Experience

# EMEA and APAC Consultant at Pentaho, A Hitachi Group Company at Pentaho, A Hitachi Group Company

July 2016 - Present

Member of the EMEA & APAC Professional Services team.

Certified Specialist - Pentaho Business Analytics Certified Specialist - Pentaho Data Integration Pentaho is a leading data integration and business analytics company with an enterprise-class, open source-based platform for diverse big data deployments. Pentaho's unified data integration and analytics platform is comprehensive, completely embeddable and delivers governed data to power any analytics in any environment.

#### University Professor at EOI Escuela de Organización Industrial

October 2016 - Present

Professor of Business Intelligence and Big Data (Profesor del Master en Business Intelligence y Big Data)

http://www.eoi.es/es/cursos/17256/master-en-business-intelligence-y-big-data-online

#### Pentaho Community Guy, Evangelist and Developer at Pentaho

March 2007 - Present

- One of the first members of the Pentaho Community in Brazil;
- First person to write a blog dedicated to Pentaho in Brazilian Portuguese;
- First person to translate and maintain the translation of Pentaho to Brazilian Portuguese and freely distribute the translation for the community;
- One of the founders of the Pentaho Community in Africa (Mozambique);
- Founder, in 2007, of IT4biz, a company dedicated to work with Open Source BI (Pentaho) in Brazil and worldwide:
- First Brazilian to participate in the World Meeting of the Pentaho Developers in Europe;
- First Pentaho Community Member to speak at Campus Party Brazil;
- Speaker in events like FISL, CONSEGI, USP ComTycho Day, etc.
- One of the Pentaho Community Members that helped organize the Community Gathering in Brazil (2011, 2012, 2013, 2014, 2015 and 2017);
- One of the most active evangelist and developer of the Open Source BI community;
- One of the first people to create dashboards using the solution created by Ingo Klose (probably in 2007 or 2008) and that was later continued by Pedro Alves, today known as CTools;
- First person in Brazil to believe in CTools, and to bring Pedro Alves to teach a CTools course in São Paulo, Brazil in 2011.
- Author of the first book about Pentaho and OSBI in Brazil in Portuguese.
- Participant at Pentaho Community Meetup (#PCM2009) in Barcelona, Spain (Oct, 2009)
- Speaker at Pentaho Community Meetup (#PCM2013) in Sintra, Portugal (Oct, 5, 2013)
- Speaker at Pentaho Community Meetup (#PCM2015) in London, UK (Nov, 7, 2015)
- Participant in the first Pentaho World in Orlando, Florida, USA (Oct, 2014)
- Speaker and Organizer at Pentaho Community Meetup in 2015 and 2016 in Madrid, Spain
- Host and Support the webpage www.pentahobrasil.com.br

#### Researcher/Data Scientist at IT4biz Global

February 2015 - June 2016 (1 year 4 months)

Based in Madrid, Spain to research about:

- SAS, Python, R, Weka, Pentaho BI Suite, Kettle/PDI
- Apache Spark, Apache Mahout, Hadoop and more.
- Machine Learning (Supervised learning, Unsupervised learning)
- Social network analysis (SNA), Dimensionality reduction, recommendation systems, semantic analysis, Natural language processing (NLP)

Working as a Data Scientist and Sr. BI Consultant

#### CEO, Founder and Sr. Principal Consultant at IT4biz Global

March 2007 - June 2016 (9 years 3 months)

- IT4biz founder:
- Pentaho Open Source Business Intelligence Specialist;
- Open Source BI Specialist;
- Experience in the whole BI Process (talking with the client, ETL, DW, KPI's, Cubes, Reports and Dashboards);
- Big Data;
- Pentaho Instructor In company training;
- Hands-on experience in application, design and development of BI Solutions;
- International experience;
- Sales experience;
- Project management experience;
- Product development experience.

Since 2007 I have been helping IT4biz adquire more than 300 clients (world wide), and deliver more than 100 successful Open Source BI Projects, trainings, support and consulting, for companies like: Petrobras, Telefonica, Policia Federal, ANP-DPF, Receita Federal, Presidência da República, Banco do Brasil, Caixa Economica Federal, Globo.com, Globosat, Jhpiego (USA/Mozambique), TRT-CE, TJMA, TCE-MT, MP-MT, PRODESP, PRODAM, Vale, Hamburg SUD, Dia %, UnB, CREMESP, VisualCue, Squadra, Deloitte Spain, etc.

#### **Consultant**

January 2014 - December 2014 (11 months)

Business Intelligence and Data Warehouse consultant, with emphasis on structuring data, development of interactive maps, dashboards, OLAP cubes, reports and Open Source BI solutions for the Agência Nacional de Saúde Suplementar (ANS).

Project page:

#### Consultant

January 2013 - December 2013 (11 months)

Business Intelligence and Data Warehouse consultant, with emphasis on structuring data, development of interactive maps, dashboards, OLAP cubes, reports and Open Source BI solutions for the Health Ministry of Brazil (MS - Ministério da Saúde / Departamento de Monitoramento e Avaliação do SUS (DEMAS)).

Project Page:

http://sage.saude.gov.br/

#### **University Professor at UNIOESTE**

July 2010 - December 2012 (2 years 5 months)

BI/DW/ETL/OLAP Professor

More infos:

http://www.inf.unioeste.br/pos/tbi/

http://www.inf.unioeste.br/pos/tbi2/

#### SugarCRM Specialist at Lampada Global

June 2006 - March 2007 (9 months)

Participated in the CRM implementation of the BANIF's Bank in Brazil;

Participated in the various CRM implementation for Small, Medium and Large companies;

I was a CRM Instructor teaching the CRM users how to use all the modules like: accounts, contacts, campaigns, opportunities, admin modules;

I developed some customizations for clients;

Implemented complex SugarCRM projects, helped new developers to get started on SugarCRM framework; Designed solution architecture for complex SugarCRM projects.

#### IT Manager

February 2005 - June 2006 (1 year 4 months)

Responsible for the IT (ERP, CRM, Network, E-mails, Website, VoIP)

#### Vice-President's and Marketing Intern at America Online

January 2002 - November 2002 (10 months)

Responsible for creating, updating and maintaining consolidated reports for the Vice President and the Loyalty Marketing Department.

My role was to consolidate reports from different sources and department (Churn, Operations, Content, Marketing, etc) into Strategic reports used by the VP.

I loved to work at AOL Brasil. But I left the company to serve for 2 years as a missionary of the LDS Church.

#### **WEB Programmer**

#### August 2000 - June 2001 (10 months)

I was part of the team that helped build www.meugrupo.com.br, a discussion group startup company that had more then 1 million users during the internet bubble period in 2000.

I worked with Cold fusion, SQL Server, HTML, Java Script as web programmer.

### Education

#### Universidad Complutense de Madrid

Master's degree, Data Mining and Business Intelligence, 2015 - 2016

#### Universidad Politécnica de Madrid

Master's degree, Artificial Intelligence, 2015 - 2017

#### **U-tad**

Specialization in Data Science, Computer Science, 2015 - 2016

**Activities and Societies:** Trabajo final: Minería de textos y análisis de sentimientos de los tweets de el proceso de impeachment en el Brasil. / Final Project: Text mining and sentiment analysis of the tweets of the impeachment process in Brazil.

#### Universidade de São Paulo

Data Analysis Using R, 2015 - 2015

#### Fundação Getúlio Vargas

Executive MBA, 2011 - 2014

#### **IE Business School**

KAM (Key Account Management), 2013 - 2013

#### **Harvard University**

Negotiation Course, 2012 - 2012

#### **Kimball University (USA)**

Dimensional Modeling in Depth, 2011 - 2011

#### Universidade Tecnológica Federal do Paraná

Specialization Course in Software Development and Java Technology, 2009 - 2010

#### Universidad de Zaragoza

Intensive Spanish Course, 2008 - 2008

#### Pontifícia Universidade Católica de São Paulo

Bachelor of Technology and Digital Media with emphasis in E-Learning Projects, 2000 - 2006

#### Escola Técnica Estadual Guaracy Silveira

Technician in Electronics and Administration, 1998 - 2000

#### Honors and Awards

Matrícula de Honor

## Caio Moreno de Souza, MSc, MBA

University Professor, Data Scientist and Consultant

caiomsouza@gmail.com



Contact Caio on LinkedIn